Guide to the Capt. Francis Micara Collection, 1944-1994 (bulk 1944-1947) UA.30.01.0011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Capt. Francis Micara collection
1944-2015 (bulk 1944-1947)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Micara, Capt. Francis
UA.30.01.0011
1.75 Linear Feet
Capt. Francis Micara was a 1944 graduate of Trinity College at Duke University and a member of numerous student organizations and activities. Collection contains material pertaining to student life at Duke during the Second World War including NROTC bulletins, performance programs, photographs, clippings, a vinyl disc, and other assorted memorabilia. In addition, the collection contains material concerning Micara's research at the Marine Laboratory at Beaufort, North Carolina, and assorted printed matter concerning class reunions.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Capt. Francis Micara Collection were received by the University Archives as a gift in 2008 and 2015.
Biographical Note
Capt. Francis Micara was a 1944 graduate of Trinity College at Duke University. While at Duke Micara was involved in numerous campus activities and organizations. He was a member of the first Naval Reserve Officers' Training Corps, Tau Psi Omega (an honorary French fraternity), Hoof 'n' Horn, the Duke Players, and Sigma Chi fraternity.
Collection Overview
Contains material pertaining to Micara's experience as a student of Trinity College at Duke University including the first NROTC Bulletin from 1941; Duke decals and stickers; playbills, clippings, photographs, and scripts from Duke Players and Hoof 'N' Horn productions including My Sister Eileen, The Laugh's the Thing, and Stand By; a 1941 Freshman Week program; photographs of Sigma Chi fraternity; a program of the Tau Psi Omega production of The Barber of Seville in French; small charms (called "keys") from several organizations of which Micara was a member including Tau Psi Omega and Sigma Chi; material from the Agar Research Program at the Marine Laboratory at Beaufort, North Carolina; and a Commencement invitation and program from the October 1944 ceremony. Also present is material from class reunions including a 33 ½ RPM record titled "Mission Possible" for the 25th class reunion of 1970; a Class of 1944 Golden Anniversary Chanticleer, 1944-1994; and biographical information on Capt. Francis Micara including an article about him in the Winter 2014 issue of the U.S. Naval Cryptologic Veterans Association's NCVA Cryptolog.
Related Material
Fraternities and Sororities Collection, 1931-2001
University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University Archives Scrapbook Collection, 1916-[ongoing]
University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hoof ‘n’ Horn Records, 1941-2006
University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Scrapbooks; Duke University -- Fraternities and sororities; Duke University -- Alumni and alumnae; Duke University. Marine Laboratory; Duke University -- Students; Duke University -- Naval Reserve Officers’ Training Corps; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Micara, Capt. Francis
- Capt. Francis Micara Collection
  - Duke decals and stickers, 1941-1943 (Box 1)
  - Class of 1944 Golden Anniversary Chanticleer, 1944-1994 (Box 1)
  - Naval Reserve Officers' Training Program Bulletin, June 1941 (Box 1)
  - "Mission Possible," Class of 1945 Reunion, 1970 June (Box 1)
  - Tau Psi Omega, honorary French fraternity, 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1942-1943; 1947 (Box 1)
  - Hoof 'n' Horn Club, Stand By, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Hoof 'n' Horn Club, The Laugh's the Thing, 1942 May (Box 1)
  - Freshman Week, program, 1941 September (Box 1)
  - Naming the Blue Devils, 1964 October (Box 1)
  - Sigma Chi fraternity, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Duke Players, My Sister Eileen, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Agar Research Program, report, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Framed photograph, Sigma Chi Fraternity, Beta Lambda Chapter, 1942 Feb. 25 (Box 2)
  - Commencement program and invitation, October 25, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Holy Bible received at Commencment ceremony, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Maryland Department of Education materials regarding volunteer service teaching English for Speakers of Other Languages (ESOL), 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Capt. Francis Micara biography and "Skipper in the Spotlight" article from NCVA Cryptolog, 2014-2015 (Box 3)
  - Pre-Med Society Key, Class of 1945 (Box 3)
  - Tau Psi Omega (Honorary French Fraternity) key, circa 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - Intramural Baseball medal, circa 1941-1944 (Box 3)
  - Hoof'n'Horn Club key, circa 1941-1944 (Box 3)
  - Sigma Chi Fraternity key, circa 1941-1944 (Box 3)
  - Class ring, class of 1945 (Box 3)
- Separated Material
  - Photographs of West Campus (four of the Chapel and one of Duke University Hospital)
    Scope and Contents note
    In the University Archives Photograph Collection.
  - Assorted clippings and "Beat Oregon State" bumper sticker.
    In the Athletics Reference Collection.
  - Five football programs
    In the Game Programs series of the Football Records.
  - Commencement Invitation, dated 1944 Oct. 25.
    In the Commencement Exercises Reference Collection.
  - Micara's Class of 1945 dink (bucket hat style) and Miller Bishop Trophy for the 1941 Duke Homecoming Best Freshman Stunt
    In the Artifacts and Relics Collection.